A Guide to the Frederic G. Melcher-Robert Frost Collection,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Frederic G. Melcher-Robert Frost Collection
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
13024
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers consisting of Robert Frost items were purchased by the University of Virginia Library from Sue A.W. Melcher, Appleton, Wisconsin, on March 31, 2004. The additional related Melcher material was given to the University of Virginia Library by Sue A.W. Melcher, Appleton, Wisconsin, on May 28, 2004.
Biographical/Historical Information
Frederic Gershom Melcher (1879-1963) was born in Malden, Massachusetts, and died on March 9, 1963, only a short while after his friend, Robert Frost. Melcher's influence in the world of books was notable, having worked as a publisher and editor for more than a half century; a bookseller at Charles E. Lauriat Company of Boston and W.K. Stewart Company, Indianapolis, Indiana (1913-1918), for almost a quarter of a century; becoming co-editor of The Publishers' Weekly in 1918, and chairman of R.R. Bowker & Company in 1958.
Melcher contributed to the promotion of good literature for children by helping develop Children's Book Week (1919), establishing the John Newbery Medal (1921) for the most distinguished contribution to American literature for children, and establishing the Caldecott Medal, for the best American picture book for children (1937).
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the personal and professional papers of Frederic G. Melcher, editor of The Publishers' Weekly, particularly those dealing with his collection of materials concerning Robert Frost, but also his relationships to other writers, publishers, and others of the book world. Frederic G. Melcher maintained a warm friendship with Robert Frost throughout his life and this relationship is reflected in the correspondence between the two men.
These papers, 1865-1963, include correspondence, printed ephemera, news clippings, photographs, manuscripts, etc., ca. 1,375 items (6 Hollinger boxes, 2.5 linear feet).
Most of the correspondence in series five is addressed to Melcher; when it is not addressed to Melcher either personally or as editor of The Publishers' Weekly, the recipient is noted in the guide. Many of the letters in this section were generated by responses to the invitation to a dinner celebrating Robert Frost's 50th birthday; by Melcher's invitation to various authors or other individuals to come and speak at Montclair, New Jersey; or to answer Melcher's 1934 question for The Publishers' Weekly concerning recommendations for essential reading in the coming year.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in five series: Series I: Robert Frost Manuscripts (Box 1) Series II: Correspondence of Robert Frost, members of the Frost Family and Frederic G. Melcher (Boxes 1-2) Series III: Miscellaneous Papers concerning Robert Frost (Boxes 2-3) Series IV: Miscellaneous Papers concerning Frederic G. Melcher and Other Authors (Boxes 3-4) Series V: Correspondence of Frederic G. Melcher and Various Authors and Publishers, arranged alphabetically by Name of Correspondent (Boxes 4-6)
All manuscripts and work by Robert Frost, hand-written, typed, or printed are found in the first series and are arranged alphabetically by title. The correspondence between Robert Frost, members of the Frost family, and Frederic G. Melcher is found in the second series and is arranged chronologically. The third series containing miscellaneous items concerning Robert Frost is arranged alphabetically by the type of material; for example advertising items; articles about Frost; a drawing; ephemera; guest lists, invitations, and programs for events involving Frost; news clippings; and photographs of Frost or Frost portraits.
The fourth series contains any non-correspondence material concerning Melcher or other authors, excluding Robert Frost, and is arranged alphabetically by type of material. The final series comprises the correspondence of Frederic G. Melcher and various authors and publishers, arranged alphabetically by the name of the correspondent and including any carbons of Melcher's letters to that person.
Contents List
- Series I: Robert Frost Manuscripts
  - Acceptance by Robert Frost, [1928], TMs, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:1)
    South Shaftsbury, Vermont with penciled notation "Original ms typed by Mr. Frost about 1928.
  - Address by Robert Frost at the Massachusetts State College Convocation, 1934 Oct 18, TMs, carbon copy, 3 pp. (Box-folder 1:2)
    With a printed program for the event.
  - Baseball: Perfect Day- A Day of Prowess by Robert Frost, 1956 Jul 23, In Sports Illustrated, printed. (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Carpe Diem by Robert Frost, n.d., AMsS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Inscribed "For Frederic Melcher".
  - Collected Poems of Robert Frost, [1930], Page Proofs (Box-folder 1:5)
    Henry Holt and Company, New York (1of 2 folders)
  - Collected Poems of Robert Frost, [1930], Page Proofs (Box-folder 1:6)
    Henry Holt and Company, New York (2 of 2 folders)
  - The Cow's in the Corn by Robert Frost, [1928], TMs, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:7)
    outh Shaftsbury, Vermont with penciled notation "Original ms typed by Mr. Frost about 1928.
  - Departmental by Robert Frost, n.d., AMsS, 3 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 1:8)
  - The Freedom of the Moon by Robert Frost, [1928], TMs, 1 p., with some autograph corrections (Box-folder 1:9)
    South Shaftsbury, Vermont with penciled notation "Original ms typed by Mr. Frost about 1928."
  - From Snow to Snow by Robert Frost, 1936, printed (Box-folder 1:10)
    Henry Holt & Company, New York.
  - The Gift Outright by Robert Frost, 1961 Mar 21, printed (Box-folder 1:11)
    Reprinted as a presentation piece by Holt, Rinehart and Winston, Inc. following the Kennedy inauguration.
  - A Group of Poems by Robert Frost, n.d., printed (Box-folder 1:12)
    Including Fragmentary Blue and Place for a Third.
  - In the Big Rain by Robert Frost, n.d., AMsS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:13)
    Inscribed " R.F. to F.M."
  - In Time of Cloud-Burst by Robert Frost, n.d., AMsS, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:14)
  - The Investment by Robert Frost, [1928], TMs, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:15)
    South Shaftsbury, Vermont with penciled notation "Original ms typed by Mr. Frost about 1928," and "In West Running Brook."
  - The Last Will and Testament of William P. Frost of Lawrence, 1901 Jan 15, TMs, 5 pp. (Box-folder 1:16)
    Essex County, Massachusetts, grandfather of Robert Frost.
  - A Line-Storm Song by Robert Frost, 1907 Oct, printed (Box-folder 1:17)
    In New England Magazine.
  - "A Monument to After Thought Unveiled" Robert Frost's Valedictory Address, June 1892, TMs, 2 pp. (Box-folder 1:18)
    Lawrence High School, 1892, published in the Lawrence High School Bulletin.
  - Neither Out Far Nor In Deep by Robert Frost in The Yale Review, 1934 Spring, printed (Box-folder 1:19)
    Issue also includes Robert Frost and the Dark Woods by J. McBride Dabbs.
  - A New Group of Poems by Robert Frost in Harper's Magazine, [post 1914] July, printed (Box-folder 1:20)
  - On a Bird Singing in its Sleep by Robert Frost in Scribner's Magazine, 1934 December, printed (Box-folder 1:21)
  - On Making Sure Anything Has Happened by Robert Frost, 1945, AMsS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:22)
    Inscribed "Dear Fred: This is a preview of our group Christmas poem for 1945. R.F."
  - Part-active Shoes by Robert Frost, 1933 April 1, AMsS, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:23)
    Inscribed "For Fred Melcher Montclair April 1 1933."
  - The Same Leaves by Robert Frost, [1928], TMs, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:24)
    South Shaftsbury, Vermont with penciled notation, "Original ms typed by Mr. Frost about 1928."
  - Several Short Poems by Robert Frost with J.J. Lankes Woodcut illustration, [1924], printed (Box-folder 1:25)
  - Three Poems by Robert Frost in The Yale Review 1934 Autumn, printed (Box-folder 1:26)
    Includes Moon Compasses, A Missive Missile, and After-Flakes.
  - The Times Table by Robert Frost, [1928], TMs, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:27)
  - To Our Ancient by Robert Frost, n.d., AMsS, 1 p., with corrections by the author (Box-folder 1:28)
    Inscribed to "F[red] M[elcher]- an old one."
  - Untitled Poem beginning "In winter in the woods alone against the trees I go," by Robert Frost, n.d., AMsS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:29)
    With typescript copy.
  - War Thoughts at Home by Robert Frost, 1918 January, TMs, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:30)
- Series II: Correspondence of Robert Frost, members of the Frost Family, and Frederic G. Melcher
  - Robert Frost, Amherst, Massachusetts, to Frederic G. Melcher, 1919 Sep 22, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:31)
    Apologizes for not answering his letters promptly and arranges to come to his home in New Jersey early in December and read to his audience, talking about "Vocal Reality." Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Robert Frost, Amherst, Massachusetts, to Frederic G. Melcher, 1919 Sep 29, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:32)
    Suggests the date of December 3 for his visit and reading. Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Robert Frost, Amherst, Massachusetts, to Frederic G. Melcher, [1919] Oct 9, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:33)
    Explains that he has made a mistake in looking at his calendar and that December 4 would be a much better date for his lecture in New Jersey, since Wednesday is his busiest day in Amherst. Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Robert Frost, Amherst, Massachusetts, to Frederic G. Melcher, 1919 Nov 18, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:34)
    Promises to make the college accommodate itself to their plans and not to worry. Frost also supposes that Carl Sandburg has sung "the Livery Stable Blues" to Melcher, furnishing an example that he had heard. Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Robert Frost to Frederic G. Melcher, on Henry Holt and Company stationery, [1919?], TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:35)
    Frost comments about Robert Chapin's illustrations for North of Boston, "His part of the book in a word, is cosmopolite. And they don't just see instantly how it goes with the work of a person who is known to hold that nine-tenths of personality is locality." Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Robert Frost, Amherst, Massachusetts, to Frederic G. Melcher, [1919 ?], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:36)
    Postpones doing a reading for Melcher as he is too tired and beset by his responsibilities to his book, college duties, family, and farming. He also suggests that Melcher let one of his friends "do a real deliberate article about my literature- a whole page or two of reconsideration." Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Robert Frost, Ann Arbor, Michigan, to Frederic G. Melcher, 1922 Dec 5, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:37)
    Answers both Melcher's letters to himself and to Lesley at the same time, saying "You have the dates and publishers of my first editions exactly right. The Holt edition of A Boy's Will and North of Boston have no additional material and no changes in the text that I am aware of. I hope to see you when I am in N.Y. just after Christmas if you are visible." Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Robert Frost, Amherst, Massachusetts, to Frederic G. Melcher, 1923 Nov 24, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:38)
    Arranges his "speaker's fee," "Whatever I come to Montclair to do it will be in exchange for your coming here once to talk to my class. That is to say you will speak for the same price I speak for. As long as no money will change hands we may as well be exorbitant and establish high records for ourselves. Suppose we make it [G.K.] Chesterton and [Sir Rabindranath] Tagore's figure- one thousand dollars." Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Frederic G. Melcher to Robert Frost, Amherst, Massachusetts, 1923 Nov 27, TL, 1 p., carbon copy. (Box-folder 1:39)
    Agrees to swap speaking dates with Frost, hoping for January 11th for Frost's visit. He also asks if he could visit Frost in February as he has to speak at Simmons College on February 6th. Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Robert Frost, Amherst, Massachusetts, to Frederic G. Melcher, 1924 Dec 10, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:40)
    With a check for $ 75.00 drawn on the First National Bank, Amherst, Massachusetts, and signed by Frost, wherein he addresses creativity, "The Harvard psychologists have been asking us writers if in our experience the act of creation doesn't just naturally articulate into a state followed by an idea followed by some work. Old Christopher Smart said that what God created had to be determined dared and done. As long as we keep to triplets I don't much care"; his debt to Melcher, sending him his eternal gratitude and the enclosed check; and their friendship, "I'd rather see you once than write you a thousand letters." Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Robert Frost, Amherst, Massachusetts, to Frederic G. Melcher, 1925 Jan 26, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:41)
    Agrees to allow Melcher to give him a "triumphal dinner" in honor of his fiftieth birthday as long as he doesn't have to look or act the age. Frost also asks him to make sure to invite the Untermeyers who had also suggested a celebration for him. Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Frederic G. Melcher to Robert Frost, Amherst, Massachusetts, 1925 Jan 29, TL, 1 p., carbon copy (Box-folder 1:42)
    Promises that the birthday celebration will be one that both he and Mrs. Frost will enjoy, plans to host it at the Hotel Brevoort, and asks for any friends he wishes to include in the guest list. Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Elinor Frost, Amherst, Massachusetts, to Frederic G. Melcher, 1925 Feb 27, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:43)
    Contributes her suggestions for Robert Frost's 50th birthday party and sends her regrets that they will not be home when he is in their area. Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Robert Frost, South Shaftsbury, Vermont, to Frederic G. Melcher, 1927 Sep 29, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l., with envelope (Box-folder 1:44)
    Wants to meet with Melcher during his trip to Springfield and discuss "that Scribners business we got started and never finished." Mentions that he has learned to drive and that he could pick him up if he came by train. Also mentions his daughter, Margery, and her poor health. Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Robert Frost telegram, Bennington, Vermont, to Frederic G. Melcher, 1928 Jul 12 (Box-folder 1:45)
    Says that the title of his next book will be West-running Brook, includes a carbon transcript of the telegram.
  - Robert Frost, Amherst, Massachusetts, to Frederic G. Melcher, 1929 Feb 9, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:46)
    Expresses his happiness that [Nicholas] Vachel [Lindsay?] is out of debt, Melcher is doing a bibliography of his work for Colophon and that he is coming to see their new farm. Frost also refers to Rudyard Kipling's monkey symbolism. Margery has taken up nursing. Possibly mentions his earliest work, Twilight, "I have a small edition of one copy of an early book of mine that nobody but Elinor and I and the printer ever saw. You'll have to say if it counts in my bibliography." Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Robert Frost, Amherst, Massachusetts, to Frederic G. Melcher, 1929 Feb 13, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:47)
    Has lost his letter so does not know the name of the man that he needs to inscribe on the two firsts sent to him to sign and has just returned from Middletown, Connecticut, where his book has gained him popularity. Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Elinor Frost, South Shaftsbury, Vermont, to Frederic G. Melcher, 1929 Jul 5, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:48)
    Hopes that Mrs. Melcher can visit also, says they are still living in the shingled cottage while repairs are being made to the farmhouse, Marjorie is in her sixth month at the hospital and is doing good work, and Lesley's baby girl is "a perfect darling." Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Robert Frost, Amherst, Massachusetts, to Frederic G. Melcher, 1930 Jan 7, ALS, 3 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 1:49)
    Discusses various editions of his books, saying "I have no first edition of the American North of Boston in blue myself." He also mentions A Boy's Will and articles about himself that might be useful in Melcher's bibliography. Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Frederic G. Melcher, to Robert Frost, Amherst College, 1930 Jan 10, Thanks Frost for his help on the bibliography he is writing and asks more questions about the first book he issued, presumably Twilight. Includes a carbon transcript of the letter. (Box-folder 1:50)
  - Robert Frost, Amherst, Massachusetts, to Frederic G. Melcher, 1930 Jan 30, ANS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:51)
    Asks to borrow his copy of The Lovely Shall Be Choosers. Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Frederic G. Melcher to Robert Frost, South Shaftsbury, Vermont, 1930 May 28, TL, carbon, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:52)
    Returns "the precious first American edition of North of Boston," lent for use in his bibliography, and mentions the use of Zadig's portrait of Frost from The Herald Tribune for his article. Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Frederic G. Melcher to Robert Frost, South Shaftsbury, Vermont, 1930 Aug 6, TL, carbon, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:53)
    Plans to mail Frost a copy of his article about Frost in The Colophon which has more orders than they can fill. He also believes that the bookseller prices for Frost material are on their way up. Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Robert Frost, Franconia, New Hampshire, to Frederic G. Melcher, [1930] Sep 1, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:54)
    Thanks Melcher for The Colophon and its impressive treatment of himself, and asks for some advice about whether he should do a series of lectures on poetry during the winter at the New School of Social Research, not being afraid of associating with either radicals or Jews. Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Frederic G. Melcher to Robert Frost, Franconia, New Hampshire, 1930 Sep 4, TL, carbon, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:55)
    Urges Frost to do the lecture series for the New School of Social Research because he has always wanted to hear what Frost has to say about the subject of poetry itself, the poet's relationship to nature, the world, and his work. He also believes that he informal nature of his lectures at the New School would be more stimulating than those given in the campus mold. Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Frederic G. Melcher to Robert Frost, South Shaftsbury, Vermont, 1930 Oct 21, TL, carbon, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:56)
    Compares his copy of the new edition of the Collected Poems printed by Random House with the trade edition from Holt, which he much prefers due to the weight of the volume, the size of the page, and the binding. Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Robert Frost to Frederic G. Melcher, [1930], ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:57)
    Refers to Melcher's article in The Colophon, "Elinor and I think this is one of the best things ever written about me and my books. I have made a few corrections and one or two suggestions."
  - Robert Frost Telegram to Frederic G. Melcher, 1931 Dec 4 (Box-folder 1:58)
    Sends his desperate plea, "For the love of literature plead with [Alfred?] Dashiell and [Henry Seidel] Canby not to blame me too much if I find myself unequal to presiding over dinners. I should have known that was what I was letting myself in for. Must be got out of office without making a noise." Melcher has written his a copy of his reply on the telegram itself, promising to intercede on his behalf with the P.E.N. officers who should be content with using his name in their masthead.
  - Frederic G. Melcher to Robert Frost, 1931 Dec 5, TL, carbon, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:59)
    Urges Frost not to be concerned about the P.E.N. dinner, although his friends would welcome his presence, he has telephoned Dashiell and all is well.
  - Robert Frost, South Shaftsbury, Vermont, to Frederic G. Melcher, 1932 Jan 18, ALS, 3 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:60)
    Expresses his appreciation for the poem on Melcher's Christmas card, voices his concerns about the family of Nicholas Vachel Lindsay and asks if money is being raised for his widow. Frost feels that they should help her find a job so she can keep the children with her. He also shares his feelings of shame at his cowardly behavior over the P.E.N. dinner during his brief term in office.
  - Robert Frost, South Shaftsbury, Vermont, to Frederic G. Melcher, 1933 Aug 4, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:61)
    Asks Melcher to give some practical advice to William, the son of Professor Otto Manthey-Zorn, Frost's "chief intimate" at Amherst, who is interested in eventually setting up a bookseller's business. Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Robert Frost, South Shaftsbury, Vermont, to Frederic G. Melcher, 1933 Nov 1, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:62)
    Encloses the poem he particularly liked (not present) which probably should have been entitled Without Prejudice to Anything, to prevent people from thinking he is disparaging machinery. He promises to copy out In Time of Cloud-Burst for Melcher but cannot answer any questions about misprints in Mountain Interval at this time. Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Robert Frost, Key West, Florida, to Frederic G. Melcher, 1934 Dec 30, ALS, 6 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 1:63)
    Discusses the cover of A Boy's Will, and Key West, Florida, as he sees it on his winter vacation, "It is a very very dead place because it has died several times. It died as a resort of pirates, than as a house of smugglers and wreckers, then as a cigar manufactury (the Cubans moved over here to get inside the tariff wall) then as a winter resort boomtown. Franklin D. himself has taken it personally in hand to give it one more life to loose." He once again mentions his Presidency of P.E.N. and claims that Dashiel has been taking his revenge on his failure by not featuring his poetry. Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Elinor Frost, Cambridge, Massachusetts, to Marguerite Melcher, [1935?] Mar 30, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:64)
    Sends a copy of her daughter Marjorie's little book of poetry. She states that thinking about the book helped her make it through the last year, although "now that it is done, I seem to feel an utter depression that is almost worse than severe physical pain." Robert is at an interval in his lectures at Harvard due to their vacation time but has been busy with other engagements. Elinor also thanks her for the winter of theatre going together.
  - Frederic G. Melcher to Robert Frost, Amherst, Massachusetts, 1935 May 7, TL, carbon, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:65)
    Sends Frost the names of two book collectors who would be thrilled to receive a copy of the Dartmouth brochure.
  - Robert Frost, Amherst, Massachusetts, to Frederic G. Melcher, 1935 Jun 19, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:66)
    Discusses the Amherst College Library, its neglect, lack of use by the boys, and the need for its promotion. Includes a carbon transcript of the letter.
  - Robert Frost to Frederic G. Melcher, [1935 Sep?], ALS, 3 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:67)